<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Rooch Network Blog</title>
        <link>https://rooch.network/blog</link>
        <description>Rooch Network Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Partnership Announcement~ zkMove <> Rooch]]></title>
            <link>https://rooch.network/blog/2023/2/10/Partnership-Announcement-zkMove</link>
            <guid>/2023/2/10/Partnership-Announcement-zkMove</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[logo配色图]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/99104408/218180814-bc9e1a02-baee-42a4-bb46-46925f33f5bb.png" alt="logo配色图" class="img_ev3q">
Rooch Network is delighted to announce its partnership with zkMove! Rooch will work closely with zkMove to bring its zk-rollup solution to Rooch’s fully interoperable, multi-chain ecosystem. Moreover we will explore new dApp usages and build the Move community together.</p><p>Zero-knowledge rollups or zk-rollups are a next-gen Layer2 scaling solution that enable blockchains to validate transactions faster and maintain low gas fees compared to traditional Layer 1s via a combination of on and off-chain processes. </p><p>zkMove is a zk-proof friendly Move language runtime environment. The initial idea of zkMove is to improve the programmability and composability of zk-proofs technology. </p><p>Some highlights of zkMove: </p><ol><li>A type safe zero-knowledge proof-friendly bytecode virtual machine </li><li>No compromise on performance while pursuing Turing completeness</li><li>Safe and efficient scaling and privacy engine</li></ol><p>For those readers interested in a deep dive into zkMove, there is a wealth of high quality information available at the zkMove medium (<a href="https://zkmove.medium.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://zkmove.medium.com/</a>). The project is also hiring qualified engineers (<a href="https://www.zkmove.net/join_us.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.zkmove.net/join_us.html</a>)!</p><p>Rooch Network is committed to its partnership with zkMove, and together we will work to deliver the holy grail of blockchain on Rooch~ a fully interoperable, multi-chain ecosystem supported in part by zkMove’s layered solution.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Partnership Announcement~ MoveBit <> Rooch]]></title>
            <link>https://rooch.network/blog/2023/2/9/Partnership-Announcement-MoveBit</link>
            <guid>/2023/2/9/Partnership-Announcement-MoveBit</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[logo-4]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/99104408/217911743-1d9f34bd-d79a-4ccb-bbb6-9f8460845b36.png" alt="logo-4" class="img_ev3q">
Rooch Network will partner with MoveBit to ensure the highest possible level of security independently verified by an expert third party. Founded by experts and professors in security, MoveBit is a blockchain security company focused on Move ecosystem security. MoveBit will soon be a household name in the security audit sector of the blockchain industry. </p><p>“MoveBit is a security audit company for the Move ecosystem with a vision to make the Move ecosystem the most secure Web3 destination. The MoveBit team is comprised of security leaders from academia and enterprise with 10 years of security experience. The team was one of the earliest contributors to the Move ecosystem, working with Move developers to set the standard for secure Move applications.” </p><p>Some of MoveBit’s recent audits include Aptos, Starcoin, Starcoin DAO, PolyNetwork, Starswap, Transit Finance, OmniBTC, MoveDID, and Cetus. </p><p>Rooch will secure independent formal verification through MoveBit audits during key stages of project development to ensure the utmost security and to create an atmosphere of trust for ecosystem participants. Security audits will be published in conjunction with MoveBit.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Partnership Announcement~ MoveFunsDao <> Rooch]]></title>
            <link>https://rooch.network/blog/2023/2/7/Partnership-Announcement-MoveFunsDAO</link>
            <guid>/2023/2/7/Partnership-Announcement-MoveFunsDAO</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[movefuns]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/99104408/217434466-c5670401-0094-4386-b0de-699e25f31650.png" alt="movefuns" class="img_ev3q">
Rooch Network has an established partnership with MoveFunsDAO, "A DAO for Move developers, with the main goal of uniting the developer community to build across multiple Move chain ecosystems." At the date of this posting, MoveFunsDAO has gathered more than 250 Move developers for the purpose of collective action and learning within the broader Move ecosystem, including Aptos, Starcoin, and Sui.  </p><p>Most notably, MoveFuns has already organized a CTF MOVEment in December 2022 alongside organizers Aptos, Pontem Network, and Movebit, and we expect it to foster many great opportunities for developers rushing to Move. </p><p>MoveFunsDao &amp; Rooch will keep a close relationship with the goal of empowering developers so the greater Move ecosystem can flourish while we grow an ever larger developer community.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hello Rooch]]></title>
            <link>https://rooch.network/blog/2022/11/27/hello-rooch</link>
            <guid>/2022/11/27/hello-rooch</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>